This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host, Jeff Doolittle.
I'm excited to invite John Ousterhout as
our guest on the show today for a
conversation about his book, A
Philosophy of Software Design. John
Ousterhout is a professor of computer
science at Stanford University. He
created the TCL scripting language and
the TK platform independent widget
toolkit. He also led the research group
that designed the experimental Sprite
operating system and the first
log-structured file system
and is also the co-creator of the Raft
consensus algorithm.
John's book, A Philosophy of Software
Design, provides insights for managing
complexity in software systems based on
his extensive industry and academic
experience.
Welcome to the show, John. Hi. Glad to
be here. Thank you for inviting me. So,
in the book, you have 15 design
principles, which we may not get to all
of them and we're not going to go
through them linearly, but these each
come out through various discussions
about complexity and and software system
decomposition. But, before we dig deeply
into the principles themselves, I want
to start by asking you
we're talking about design styles, so is
there just one good design style or are
there many and and how do you kind of
distinguish those? It's a really
interesting question. When I started
writing the book, I I wondered that
myself. And one of the reasons for
writing the book was to plant a flag out
there and see how many people disagreed
with me. And I was curious to see if
people would come to me and say, "Show
me No, I I do things a totally different
way." and could actually convince me
that in fact their way was also good.
Cuz it seemed possible, you know, there
are other areas where different design
styles all work well. They may be
totally different, but each works in its
own way. And so, it seems possible that
could be true for software. So, I I have
an open mind about this, but what's
interesting is that as the book's been
out there a few years and I get feedback
on it, so far I'm not hearing anything
that would suggest that, for example,
the principles in the book are
situational or personal and that there
are alternate universes that are also
valid. And so, my current hypothesis, my
working hypothesis, is that in fact
there are these absolute principles.
But, I'd be delighted here if anybody
else thinks they have a different
universe that also works well. I haven't
seen one so far. Well, and just that
mindset right there I want to highlight
as as, you know, someone who does
design, that it's more important that
you put your ideas out there to be
invalidated because you really can't
ever prove anything, you can only
invalidate a hypothesis. So, I love that
was your attitude with this book, too.
You may say things that sound axiomatic,
but you're really putting out a theory
and asking people and inviting critical
feedback and conversation, which is
really the only way the discovery of
human knowledge works anyway. So, in the
software development life cycle, when do
you design? Oh boy, that's that may be
the most fundamental question in all of
software design. Well, as you know,
there are many many approaches to this.
In the extreme,
you do all your design up front. This is
sometimes been caricatured by calling it
the waterfall model, although that's a
bit of an exaggeration, but but in the
most extreme case, you do all design
before any implementation and then after
that the design is fixed. Well, we know
that approach doesn't work very well
because one of the problems with
software is these systems are so
complicated
that no human can visualize all of the
consequences of a design decision. You
simply cannot design a computer system
up front, a system of any size, and get
it right. There will be mistakes. And
so, you have to be prepared to fix
those. If you're not going to fix them,
then you're going to pay tremendous
costs in terms of complexity and bugs
and so on. So, you have to be prepared
to do some redesign after the fact. Then
there's the other extreme, and so people
have recognized this that we should do
design in more and more of an iterative
fashion. Do a little bit of design, a
little bit of coding, and then some
redesign, a little bit more coding. And
that can get taken to the extreme where
you essentially do no design at all. You
just start coding and you fix bugs.
This is sort of design by debugging.
That would be a maybe an extreme
caricature of the Agile model. It
sometimes feels like it's becoming so
extreme that there's no design at all.
And that's wrong, also. So, the truth is
somewhere in between. I can't give you a
precise formula for exactly when, but
but as you do a bit of design
up to the point where you really can't
visualize what's going to happen
anymore, and then you have to build and
see the consequences.
And then you have may have to go back
and fix some old design, and then maybe
you add on some more parts and so on.
So, I think design is a continuous thing
that happens throughout a life the life
cycle of a project. It never ends. You
do some at the beginning. It's always
going on as subsystems become more
mature, typically you spend less and
less time redesigning those. You're not
going to rebuild every subsystem every
year. But, recognize the fact that you
may someday discover that even a very
old system that you thought was perfect
and had everything right, actually now
no longer is serving the needs of the
system and you have to go back and
redesign it. Are there some real-world
examples that you can pull from that
kind of demonstrate this process of of
design or or maybe things that have
happened historically that sort of
reflect this this revisiting of design
assumptions previously and then
attacking them in a different way over
time or or refining designs as we go?
Great question. I can answer a slightly
different question, which my students
often ask me, which is how many times
does it take you to get a design right?
Okay. It's not quite the same question.
So, my experience is that when I design
something, it typically takes about
three tries before I get the design
right. But, I do design first design and
then I start implementing it and it
typically falls apart very quickly on
implementation. So, I go back and do a
major redesign. And then the second
design looks pretty good, but even that
one needs additional fine-tuning over
time. And so, the third iteration is
fine-tuning. And then, once you have
that, then systems,
I think that those classes or modules
tend to stand the test of time pretty
well. But, now your question was is
there something where where you have a
module that really worked well? I don't
even necessarily mean software, by the
way, right? Like maybe like maybe real
world or or examples of of how
iterations in designs have changed and
and had to be revisited over time. Well,
I think the classic cause of that is
technology change. That when the
underlying technologies for how we build
something change, often
that will change what designs are
appropriate. And so, for example, in
cars, we're seeing this with the advent
of electrical vehicles. That's changing
all sorts of other aspects of the design
of cars. Like the structure of the car
changes now because the main structural
element is this battery that lives in
this very flat, heavy thing at the
bottom of the car. That has a
fundamental impact on the design of the
car. Or another example is the the rise
of large screen displays. And now we're
seeing the instrument clusters in cars
changing fundamentally because you
there's this large display that is is
replacing a lot of other stuff. And of
course, in computers, you know, we've
seen design change with with radical new
technologies. The advent of the personal
computer caused a whole bunch of new
design issues to come along. And the
arrival of networks and the web, again,
changed a whole bunch of design issues.
So, technology, I think, has a very big
impact on design. Yeah, and you
mentioned cars, you know, if you think
about the last 100 and what's it been,
140 years maybe since the first bespoke
automobiles were were created and the
technology certainly has changed from
horses and buggies or horseless
carriages to to what we have now. And I
think definitely software is is
experiencing that as well. You know, now
with distributed cloud technologies,
that's just a whole another rethinking
of how things are designed in in order
to tackle the the challenges of
complexity on complexity distributed
systems in the cloud seem to introduce.
So, speaking of complexity, there's a
few principles in the book that
specifically relate to complexity. So,
in your experience, you know, you've
said a few things like, for example, we
need to recognize that complexity is
incremental and you have to sweat the
small stuff. And you mentioned another
principle of pulling complexity
downward. So, first, maybe speak a
little bit about the nature of
complexity and how that affects software
systems and then let's explore these
these design principles in a little more
detail. Yes. So, first, let me let me
first
make clear about what I think is the
uber principle, you know, the the one
principle to rule the all rule them all
is complexity. That's I mean, that's to
me that's what design is all about.
That's the fundamental that we're trying
to build systems
that limit their complexity. Because the
reason for that is that the only thing
that limits
what we can build in software is
complexity. Really, that's the
fundamental limit is our ability to
understand the systems. We're the
computer system will allow us to build
software systems that are far too large
for us to understand. Memory sizes are
large enough, processors are fast
enough. We can build systems that could
have tremendous functionality if only we
could understand them well enough to
make these systems work. So, everything
is about complexity. So, so by the way,
all of the principles in the book are
all about managing complexities
complexity. And I would also say that if
you ever get to a point where it seems
like one of these principles I put
forward conflicts with complexity,
with managing complexity,
go with managing complexity. Then the
the principle is a bad principle for
that situation.
So, I I just want to say before we
start, that's that's the overall thing.
So, everything else relates to that in
some way. Then the second thing I think
that is important to realize about
complexity is that it is incremental.
That is, it isn't that you make one
fundamental mistake that causes your
system's complexity to grow without
bound. It's
it's lots of little things. And often
things that you think,
"This isn't that big of a deal. I'm not
going to sweat this issue. It's It's
only a little thing. Yeah, I I know,
it's a kludge, but it's not really big.
This won't matter." And of course, no
one of them matters, that's true. But,
the problem is that you're doing dozens
of them a week and each of the 100 other
programmers on your project is doing
dozens of them a week. And together they
add up. And so, so what that means is
that once complexity arises, also, it's
extremely difficult to get rid of it
because there's no single fix. There
isn't one thing you can go back and
change that will get rid of all that
complexity that's been accumulated over
the years. You have to change hundreds
or thousands of things and most
organizations don't have the
courage and level of commitment to go
back and make major changes like that.
So then you just end up living with it
forever. Well, and you mentioned before
the human propensity to go for the short
term and I imagine that has a
significant impact here as well. So you
say complexity is incremental, you have
to sweat the small stuff. So
how much sweating is appropriate and how
do you avoid say analysis paralysis or
or I don't know. I I I just imagine
people saying there's they're concerned
that all progress will halt if we stop
to worry about the incremental addition
of complexity. How do you how do you
fend that off or or deal with that?
First, I'm sure people make those
arguments. I'm sure a lot of people say
to their bosses, well, do you want me to
go back and clean up this code or do you
want me to meet my deadline for this
Friday? And almost all bosses will say,
okay, I guess we have to meet the
deadline for this Friday. The question I
would ask is, how much can you afford?
Think of it like an investment.
That you're going to spend a little bit
more time today
to improve the design to keep complexity
from creeping in
and that in return you're going to save
time later.
So it's like this investment is
returning interest in the future. What I
would argue is how much I would ask is
how much can you afford to invest? Could
you afford to let your schedules slip 5
or 10%?
Every schedule is going to be 5 or 10%
slower than we might have thought, but
we're going to get a much better design.
And then the question is, well, that
maybe that will actually gain you back
more than 5 or 10%. Maybe with that
better design you'll actually run your
code twice as fast in the future.
And so it has more than paid for itself.
Now, the challenge with this argument is
no one's ever been able to quantify how
much you get back from the good design.
And so I believe it's actually
significant, far more than the cost the
extra cost of trying to make your design
better.
And I think many people believe that.
But no one's been able to do experiments
that can prove that. Maybe that's also
another one of the one of the reasons
why people put off doing the design
because
I can I can measure the 5%
slip in my current deadline. I can't
measure the 50% or 100% faster coding
that we get in the future. Yeah, and
this is where I start to think about
characteristics like quality because
from my perspective a quality problem is
when you're having to worry about
something that you shouldn't have had to
worry about. So, you know, you mentioned
cars before, right? So what's a quality
problem in a car? Well, there's
something that is not now your concern
as a driver that should not be your
concern.
But what's interesting too is there's
scheduled maintenance for a car and so
putting that off for too long is going
to lead not to a quality problem because
of the manufacturer, but it's going to
lead to a quality problem because of
your negligence. And I wonder if you
think a similar thing applies to
software where this if we're negligent,
maybe we can't immediately measure the
effects of that, but downstream we can
measure it in terms of pain. I still
fear it's hard to measure it, but I
agree with the notion of scheduled
maintenance. That I understand there are
practical realities. Sometimes some
things just have to get done and get
done fast. You know, if a critical bug
that has your customers offline, they're
not going to be very comfortable with
this argument that well, it's going to
take us a couple of extra weeks because
we want to make sure our design is good
for our projects 2 years from now.
So I recognize that. I understand people
have to work under real world
constraints. But then I would say
try and find some time, some budget
where later on people can go back and
clean things up after you hit the
deadline. Maybe the next week is used to
clean up some of the problems that you
knew you had introduced at the last
minute. Or some fraction of your team, 5
or 10% their job is to go back and do
code cleanups rather than writing new
code.
And so it's not an all or nothing. You
don't have to stop the world and I argue
you you don't have to do heroics
to have great design. It's just
in the same way that complexity builds
up piece by piece, you can do good
design piece by piece. Lots of little
steps you take along the way to make the
design a little bit better. You don't
have to fix everything all at once. So
that's the incremental factor meaning
complexity is incremental, but it sounds
like you're saying we can also
incrementally address it as we go. So
another principle regarding complexity
you mentioned pulling complexity
downward. Can you explain a little bit
more about what that means and and how
people apply that principle? Yes,
actually I I originally had a different
name for that. I called it the martyr
principle. Okay. Which and
people told me that was a little bit too
inflammatory for me maybe, but I so I
took it out, but I I still like it. So
the basic idea I'm I'm not referring to
religious jihad when I say martyr. Sure.
I'm thinking of the definition where a
martyr is someone who takes suffering on
themselves so that other people can be
happier and live a better life.
And I think of that's our job as
software designers.
That we take these big gnarly problems
and try and find solutions to them that
are incredibly simple and easy for other
people to use.
And actually honestly, I don't think of
it as suffering. It's actually what
makes software fun is solving those hard
problems. But but this idea that pull
the hard problems downward
as opposed to the other philosophy is,
well, as a programmer I'm just going to
solve all the stuff that's easy
and then I'll just punt upwards all the
other
issues. A classic example is just
throwing tons of exceptions for every
possible slightly strange condition
rather than just figuring out how to
handle those conditions so you don't
have to throw an exception. And so this
gets back to managing complexity again.
So the idea is that we want to somehow
find ways of hiding complexity. So if I
can build a module that solves really
hard gnarly problems
maybe it has to have some complexity
internally, but it provides a really
simple clean interface for everybody
else in the system to use
then that's reducing the overall
complexity of the system because only a
small number of people will will be
affected by the the complexity inside
the module. Yeah, that sounds very
similar to what one of my mentors calls
technical empathy. I I can guess what
the meaning of that is that I I like the
idea. Yes. Yes, which which personally I
call the Homer Simpson principle where
there's this wonderful and you can find
a a GIF of it online somewhere or not a
GIF, but a a short YouTube video of
Homer Simpson with a bottle of vodka in
one hand and a bottle of mayonnaise in
the other and and Marge says, "I don't
think that's such a good idea." And he
says, "Oh, that's that's a problem for
future Homer. Well, I don't envy that
guy." And he proceeds to consume the
mayonnaise and vodka. And so the the
irony is, you know, you mentioned
carrying the the suffering which of
course in this case can't be fun.
Carrying the complexity yourself, right?
Embracing the complexity yourself on
behalf of others so they don't have to
experience it. Ironically, a lot of
times when you don't do that, you're not
having technical empathy for your future
self because you're going to come back
and say, "Oh, I wrote this."
And then you end up carrying the pain
anyway. Actually, another great example
of that is configuration parameters.
Rather than figure out how to solve a
problem, just export 12 files to the
user. They
say and then and not only are you
punting the problem, but you can say,
"Oh, I'm actually doing you a favor
because I'm giving you the ability to
control all of this so you're going to
be able to produce a really great
solution for yourself." But
often times I think the reason people
export the parameters is because they
don't actually have any idea how to set
them themselves. And they're somehow
hoping that the user will somehow have
more knowledge than they do and be able
to figure out the right way to set them.
But more often than not, in fact, the
user has even less knowledge to set
those than the designer did. Oh, yeah.
And 12 parameters, you know, 12
factorial is somewhere in the tens of
billions. So good good luck figuring
out, you know, even with seven there's
5,040 possible combinations and
permutations of those. So yeah, as soon
as you export, you know, seven
configuration parameters to your end
user, you've just made their life
incredibly challenging and complex.
That's an example of pushing complexity
upwards. Mhm. That's perfect.
solve the problem, I force my users to
solve it. And you also mentioned in
there exceptions and just throwing
exceptions everywhere which relates to
another one of the design principles
which is defining errors and special
cases out of existence. So what are some
examples of of how you've applied this
or or seen this principle applied? So
first I need to make a disclaimer on
this one. This is a principle that can
be applied sometimes, but I have noticed
as I see people using it they often
misapply it.
So let me first talk about how you can
apply it and then we can talk about how
it's how it's misapplied.
Some great examples, one of them was
the unset command in the Tcl scripting
language. So Tcl has a command unset
that deletes a variable.
When I wrote Tcl, I thought, no one in
their right mind would ever delete a
variable that doesn't exist. That's got
to be an error.
And so I threw an exception
whenever somebody deletes a variable
that doesn't exist.
Well, it turns out
people do this all the time.
Like the classic example is you're in
the middle of doing some work, you
decide to abort, you want to clean up
and delete the variables. But you may
not know remember you may not know
exactly which variables have been
created or not. So you just go through
and try and delete them all. And so
what's ended up happening is that if you
look at Tcl code, virtually every unset
command in Tcl
is actually encapsulated inside a catch
command that will catch the exception
and throw it away. So what I should have
done was simply redefine
the the meaning of the unset command.
Change instead of deleting a variable
it's the new definition is make a
variable not exist. And if you think
about the definition that way
then if the variable already doesn't
exist, you're done. There's no problem.
It's perfectly natural. There's no
error.
So that just defines the error out of
existence.
A a better an even better example I
think is deleting a file. So what do you
do if somebody wants to delete a file
when a file is open? Well,
Windows took a really bad approach to
this. It said you can't do that.
And so if you've used a Windows system,
you've probably been in the situation
where you tried to delete a file or
program tried to delete a file and you
get an error saying, "Sorry, I delete
file. File's in use."
And so what do you do? Then you go
around, you try and
close all the programs that maybe have
that file open. I've been at times where
I couldn't figure out which program had
the file open, so I just had to reboot
before I could delete the file.
And then it turned out it was a demon
that had the file open, and the demon
got restarted. So Unix took a beautiful
approach to this. It's It's really a
lovely piece of design.
Which is they said, "Well, it's no
problem. You can delete a file when it's
open.
What we'll do is we'll remove the
directory entry. The file is completely
gone as far as the rest of the world is
concerned, but we'll actually keep the
file around as long as someone has it
open.
And then when the last process closes
the file, then we'll delete it." That's
a perfect solution to the problem.
Now, people complain about Windows, and
so there've been various changes made
over the years, and I I don't remember
exactly where Windows stands today, but
at one point they had modified it so
that in fact you could set a flag saying
it's okay to delete this file while it's
open. And then Windows would do that,
but it kept the directory entry around.
And so you couldn't create a new file
until the file had finally been closed.
And then once the file was closed, the
file would go away, the directory entry
would go away, and then you could delete
it. So a lot of programs like make,
which, you know, remove a file and then
try and recreate, they wouldn't work.
They still wouldn't work if the file was
open.
So they just kept defining errors,
creating new errors that caused problems
for people. Whereas Unix had this
beautiful solution of just eliminating
all possible error conditions. Well, and
that is right back to pulling complexity
downward, because what do exceptions do?
They bubble upward. So by allowing them
to bubble up, you're you're violating
that previous principle that we
discussed. Now, now I need to do this
disclaimer though, so people don't go
off and make a whole lot of mistakes. I
I mentioned this principle to students
in my class, and actually I'm at the
point now where I may
I may even stop mentioning this to the
students, because for some reason, no
matter how much I disclaim this, they
start They seem to think that they can
simply define all errors out of
existence.
In the first project for my class,
inevitably they'll be brought It's a
project building a network server where
there are tons of exceptions that can
happen. You know, servers crash, network
connections fail.
There will be projects
that do not throw a single exception or
even check for errors. And I'll say,
"What's going on here?" And they'll say,
"Oh, we just defined those all out of
existence."
And I'll say,
"No, you just ignored them. That's
different."
So
So I do want to say that errors happen.
You know, most of the time
you have to actually deal with them in
some way. But sometimes, if you think
about it, you can actually define them
away. So think of this as a spice, you
know, that you use in very small
quantities in some places, but if you
use it too much, it
you end up with something that tastes
pretty bad. Yeah, and I remember one of
the, you know, early mistakes that a lot
of programmers make when they first get
started is empty catch blocks.
When you see this littered throughout
the code, that is not what you mean when
you're saying define errors out of
existence.
You're not saying swallow and ignore,
define.
I don't think this is one of the design
principles, but it triggers in my
thinking as well that if there is an
exceptional condition, you do want to
let it fail fast. In other words, you
want to find out, and you you want
things to stop functioning. Like bring
bring it down if there's an exception,
and then figure out how to keep it from
coming down in the first place, instead
of just pretending nothing went wrong.
Well, this gets at another important
thing. One of the most I think one of
the most important ideas in doing
design, which I think is true in any
design environment, software, or
anything else,
is you have to decide what's important
and what's not important. And if you
can't decide If you think everything is
important, or if you think nothing's
important, you're going to have a bad
design.
Good designs pick a few things that they
decide are really important, and they
emphasize those. You bring those out,
you don't hide them, you probably
present them up to users.
And so in soft Software design is the
same thing. If an exception really
matters,
you probably do need to do something.
You probably do need to pass it back to
the user. You probably want to highlight
it, make it really clear
that this thing happened.
And then other things that are less
important, then those are the things you
try and hide or encapsulate inside a
module so that nobody else has to see
them. The thing I tell my students over
and over again is, "What's important?
What's the most important thing here?"
Pick that out, and and focus your design
around that. Yeah, that and as you
mentioned previously, what what can I do
to handle this exceptional condition
right here instead of passing it further
along, especially in a case where, like
you mentioned even in your design of of
tickle, where the exception really
shouldn't be happening, because if the
outcome is item potent, meaning
performing the same action twice returns
in the same outcome, then why is that an
exceptional condition?
Why should it be? Yeah, it was just And
then why should you pass that up?
Because you're just giving people
useless information that they can't do
anything about.
Yes, I made something important that
wasn't really important. That was my
error. Yes. Yes. Yeah, and I think
that's a big risk when we're designing
systems that we can fall into that trap.
So it's a good thing to watch out for.
Maybe that's the individual one. Don't
make Don't make unimportant things
important.
And vice versa.
So one of the mistakes people make in
abstraction
is they hide things that are important.
They don't expose things that are really
important. And then the module becomes
really hard to use, because you can't
get at the stuff you need. You don't
have the controls you need. You're not
aware of the things you need.
So again, it's all about
it's a two-way street, where again you
want to emphasize what's important.
Don't hide that.
And then hide what's unimportant. And by
the way, ideally, you know, the best
designs have the fewest number of things
that are important.
If you can do that. But it's like
Einstein's old saying about everything
should be as simple as possible, but no
simpler. Again,
you can't just pretend something's
unimportant when it really is. You have
to figure out what really is important.
That's right. And that takes creativity
and and effort. It doesn't just
magically come to you out of thin air.
Yeah, and insight and experience, too,
in terms of knowing how people are going
to use your system and Yeah, I think
that's important, too. Insight and
experience as it pertains to design is
is going to be important. When you're
first getting started, you're you're
going to have more challenges, but the
longer you do this, I imagine I I'm
assuming this is your experience as
well, is that it does become somewhat
easier to design things as you go when
they're similar to things you've
experienced before. It It does. One of
the things I tell my students I tell
them if if you're not very experienced,
figuring out what's important is really
hard. You just You may not have the
knowledge to know.
And so then what do you do?
And so what I tell people is, make a
guess. Don't just Don't just ignore the
question. Think about it.
Make your best guess, and commit to
that.
It's like form a hypothesis, and then
test that hypothesis. You know, as you
build the system, see, was I right or
was I wrong? And that act of com-
committing, make a commitment, this is
what I believe
so far,
and then testing it, and then learning
from it, that's how you learn. But if
you don't ever actually
make that mental commitment, I think try
and figure it out, make your best guess,
and then test that, then I think it's
hard to learn. Right. And what you're
saying there, I think, is more than just
test your implementation, it's test your
design. Absolutely, yeah. Which is makes
a lot of sense. Another related thing I
tell my students is, related to testing
the design is, your code will speak to
you if only you will listen.
And this gets at one of the things in
the book that
that I think is most useful for for
beginners is red flags. That things you
can see that will tell you that you're
probably on the wrong track in terms of
design. You may need may need to revisit
something. But becoming aware of those
so that you can get feedback from your
systems themselves. Use what you can
observe about a system in order to learn
what's good and bad, and also in order
to improve your design skills.
Absolutely. And there's a great list of
some of those red flags at the at the
back of your book as a reference for for
people. You've mentioned a couple times
the word modules, and maybe it would be
helpful before we dig in a little bit
more into modules and layers. What do
those words mean when you use them to
kind of help frame the the upcoming
section here? I think of a module as
something that encapsulates a particular
set of related functions.
And I define modules really in terms of
this complexity thing again. That's the
way I think of them. The module is a
vehicle
for reducing overall system complexity.
And the goal of a module, which I think
is the same as the goal of abstraction,
is to provide a simple way to think
about something that's actually
complicated.
That's the idea. The notion that
that you have a very simple interface to
something with a lot of functionality.
And in the book I used the word deep to
describe modules like that. Thinking of
I I used the analog of a rectangle,
where the area of the rectangle is the
functionality of a module, and the the
length of its upper edge is the
complexity of the interface. And so the
ideal modules are those that have very
small interfaces, so it's a very tall,
skinny rectangle. Small interface and a
lot of functionality, or anything.
Shallow modules are those that have a
lot of interface
and not much functionality.
And the reason that's bad is because
that interface is complexity.
That the interface is the complexity
that a module imposes on the rest of the
system.
And so we'd like to minimize that. So
because lots of people will have to be
aware of that interface. Not so many
people will have to be aware of any
internal complexity of the module. Yeah,
and I saw this early in my career, and I
still see it a lot, but not on systems
I'm working on, because I don't do it
anymore. But in the early days, what you
could call forms over data applications,
where it was all here's just a bunch of
data entry screens, and then you can run
reports. And when you do that, where
does all the complexity reside, and
where does all the tacit knowledge live?
Well, it lives in the end users. So then
you have these highly trained end users
that when they leave the company,
everybody gets terrified, because there
went everything and all the knowledge.
And And now it seems that what we've
done is we've said, "Well, let's at
least move that complexity into the
application." But it ends up in front
end applications, which are now just
having all that complexity inside them,
and they're trying to orchestrate
complex interactions with a bunch of
different systems, and that's not really
solving the problem either. So, I
imagine when you say module, you don't
mean either of those two things, you
mean get it get it even further down,
further away, right? In other words,
like you don't want the dashboard of
your car controlling your engine timing,
but it seems to me that's the state of a
lot of web applications where the
front-end is controlling the system in
ways that really the system should be
owning that complexity on behalf of the
front-end or the end user. I think that
sounds right. Again, you'd like to
you'd like to separate the functions out
so you don't have to have one place that
has a whole lot of knowledge because
that's going to be a whole lot of
complexity for that one place.
Now, it's a little hard in an
application,
a lot of stuff comes together at the top
layer, at the GUI layer.
You know, and so that layer may have to
have at least some knowledge of lots of
other parts of the system because it's
combining all those together to present
to the user. So, it's a little harder
it's a little harder to get modularity
or sort of deep classes when you're
talking about the user interface layer.
I think and I think that's just part of
that is just structural because of the
nature of the
uh of what it does. But, you'd like to
have as little of the system as possible
have that flavor. Mhm. So, modules, you
mentioned they're basically taking
complexity and they're reducing the
experience of that complexity and in for
the consumer that module in essence.
Hiding it, right? Right, right, which
goes back to the Parnas paper as well,
which we'll link to in the show notes.
And so then, talk a little bit about
layers and how those relate then to
modules. I tend to think of layers as
methods that call methods that call
methods or classes that depend on
classes that depend on classes.
And so that creates potentially a
layered system, although
personally, when I code, I don't really
think about layers that much. I don't
think about a system as having discrete
layers because the systems tend to be so
complicated that
that diagram would be very complex
where, you know, sometimes layer A
depends on layer B, and sometimes it may
be also depend on layer C at the same
time while B depends on C. And that
graph of usage
to me has always felt very complex and a
and I'm not sure I really have to
understand that so much.
If you've really got modularity,
that is these classes encapsulate well,
I think I would argue that that that's a
more important
way of thinking about systems than in
terms of the layers. Mhm. Well, it
sounds like two when you're saying
layers there, there's there's a
relationship to dependencies there. If a
method has to call another method on
another class or another interface,
there's a dependency relationship there.
Yeah, yeah, I I definitely I would agree
those are important. It's just it's very
hard,
I think, to think systemically about all
the dependencies. There's no way you
could look at a complex system
and in your mind visualize all the
dependencies between classes. Right, or
necessarily have all dependencies have a
certain classification of a certain
layer, which kind of classic N-tier
architecture tried to do, but maybe in
if I'm understanding you correctly,
maybe that's uh
that's pretending we're dealing with
complexity, but we're maybe actually
not. Yeah, or just that systems big
systems really don't decompose naturally
into perfect layers.
Occasionally it works, you know,
the TCP protocol is layered on top of
the IP network protocol, which is
layered on top of some underlying
Ethernet transport system. So, there the
layering works pretty well, and you can
think about three distinct layers.
But, in general, I don't think large
software systems tend to break down
cleanly into a perfect layer diagram.
Yeah, and I think part of the reason you
just mentioned, you know, TCP, I think
HTTP is another example of what I've
read recently you can call the narrow
waist. And uh that's another design
approach to things is if everything
boils down to byte streams or or text,
there's a narrow waist there. And from
my experience, it seems that layering
can really work really well in that kind
of a context, but not every system that
we're building necessarily has that
narrow of a waist. And maybe layering
doesn't quite apply as well in in those
other situations. I would say HTTP is a
great example of a deep module.
Mhm. Very simple interface. The basic
protocol is very simple, relatively easy
to implement,
and yet it has allowed tremendous
interconnectivity in the in the web and
the internet. So many different systems
have been able to communicate with each
other effectively using HTTP. It's a
really great example of
hiding a lot of complexity, making
tremendous functionality possible with a
pretty simple interface. Yes, and I
would say it's also a classic example of
just how much
incidental complexity we can add on top
of something that isn't itself
necessarily complex.
Maybe the corollary here is that people
will always find ways of of making
systems more complicated than you would
like. Oh, that is absolutely true. Yes,
especially when there's deadlines
Okay, so I think we have a better
understanding of modules and layers
then. So, maybe talk a little bit more
about what it means that modules should
be deep. Like you mentioned a second ago
about, you know, the sort of narrow and
there's a simple interface. So, explore
that a little bit more for us so
listeners can start thinking about how
they can design modules that tend to be
deep rather than shallow.
Okay, so there's two ways you can think
about a module. One is in terms of what
functionality it provides, and one is in
terms of the interface. But, let's let's
start with the interface cuz I think
that's the key thing. The interface
is everything that anyone needs to know
in order to use the module. And to be
clear, that's not just the signatures of
the methods. Yes, those are part of the
interface, but there's lots more.
You know, side effects or expectations
or dependencies. You must invoke this
method before you invoke that method.
Any piece of information that a user has
to know in order to use the module,
that's part of its interface. And so
when you're thinking about the
complexity of an interface, it's
important to think about all that.
Functionality is harder to define.
That's just what it does. Maybe it's the
right way to think about a system with a
lot of functionality. Maybe it's that it
can be used in many, many different
situations to perform different tasks.
Maybe that's the right way to think
about it. I don't have as good a
definition. Maybe you have thoughts
about how would you define the
functionality of a module, you know,
what makes one module more functional
than another? Well, I think my my first
thought is it relates somewhat back to
what you said before about I call the
technical empathy, but when you were
referring before to the martyr
principle, right, pulling complexity
downward. The more complexity you can
contain in a module through a simpler
interface, I think would tend to add
towards that richness and that depth.
So, you know, for example, the power
outlet is a wonderful example of an
amazing abstraction, and and I spent a
lot of time thinking about it because
it's a great way I think too to help us
think about how to simplify our software
systems. I can plug any and all
appliances into that simple power
outlet. If I go to another country, I
just need an adapter, and I can still
plug into it. And where's the power
coming from behind it? Well, I don't
know. I know the options perhaps, but do
I know exactly where this electron came
from? I don't, right? So, and there's a
ton of complexity then that's
encapsulated in that very simple
interface. So, for me, that that's how I
kind of view as a deep module would be
one that
gives me a very simple interface by
shielding me from a ton of complexity
that I may want to think about and know
about, right? For example, if I'm
environmentally conscious, I may care
about where my power is coming from.
But, when I go to plug in the vacuum,
I'm probably not asking myself that
question at that moment. Yes, another
way of thinking about it is really good
modules,
they just do the right thing.
Don't have to be told, they just do the
right thing. Here's an example. I I can
tell you I I know for a fact what is the
world's deepest interface.
And what it is, it's the garbage
collector. Because when you add a
garbage collector to a system, it
actually reduces the interface. It has a
negative interface because you no longer
have a free method you have to call.
Before you introduce the garbage
collector, you had to call free. Now you
don't. There is no interface to a
garbage collector.
But, it just sneaks around behind the
scenes and figures out what memory is
not being used and returns it to the
pool so you can allocate from it. So,
that's an example of just do the right
thing. I don't care how you do it, just
figure out when I'm done with memory and
put it back in the free pool. That's a
great point. So, in that case, the
interface is effectively zero from the
standpoint of the end user. Well, maybe
it's a negative. It's still called GC
suppress finalize when you're disposing,
but that's a whole other conversation
for another day, but yes.
And and you're right that it does hide a
lot of complexity from you in that
sense. You know, I think as well of of,
you know, SQL databases that that give
you a what's supposed to be a simple
human readable language, but the
complexity of what it does under the
covers of query planning and and, you
know, which indexes to use and these
sorts of things and trying to reduce
table scanning. That's a lot of
complexity that's shielded behind what
what is a much simpler language in
comparison to what's actually happening
under the covers. Oh, yeah, SQL is a
beautiful example of a very deep
interface. Another one, one of my
favorites, is a spreadsheet.
What an amazingly simple interface. You
think about just we just have a
two-dimensional grid in which people can
enter numbers or formulas. You can
describe it in in like that in three
sentences. Now, of course, people have
added lots of bells and whistles over
the years, but the basic idea is so
simple and yet it's so incredibly
powerful. The number of things people
can use spreadsheets for is just
astounding. It is. And Microsoft Excel
now has a function called lambda, and so
therefore spreadsheets are now Turing
complete.
But,
interestingly there, with great power
comes great responsibility, and I'm sure
you've seen as I have some of the
nastiest spreadsheets you could possibly
imagine, and that's probably because
design wasn't really a thought. It was
just implement, implement, implement. I
don't believe there is any way to
prevent people from producing
complicated systems.
And sometimes
or for that matter, to prevent people
from introducing bugs.
And sometimes systems go out of the way
to try and prevent people from doing bad
things. But, in my experience, as often
as not, those systems also prevent
people from doing good things.
And so I think we should design to make
it as easy as possible to do the right
thing,
and then not worry too much if people
abuse it cuz that's just going to
happen. You can't stop them. I mean, you
hope that with some code reviews, which
from what we're talking to, it you know,
suggests to me that your code reviews
should also be design reviews. That
those could There could be mechanisms to
try to check this, but you can't be
paranoid and try to prevent any and all
bugs in in your system, right?
Absolutely. Yeah. So, speak a little bit
more to that. You know, I mentioned code
review as a time not just for reviewing
the code and the implementation, but
also the the design. So, how do you
encourage students or have you
experienced that before where you try to
introduce a design review as well in the
code review process? Well, to me, I just
don't separate those. When I review
people's code, if they ask me to review
their code, they're getting design
feedback as well.
Now, you know, there may be times in a
project where
they just aren't in a position to take
that design feedback and act on it. But
when I review, I'm going to provide it
anyway. And I would argue people should
anyway, just so that people are aware
about it. And even if you can't fix it
today, you can put it on your to-do list
that maybe when you get a little clean
up time after the next deadline, you can
go back and get it. So, I I just I feel
like code reviews ought to be holistic
thing that look at You want to find all
of the possible ways of improving the
software.
We shouldn't limit it to just certain
kinds of improvements. Yeah, I think
that's a great way of looking at it. And
and also recognizing that as you become
more familiar with the design and you
improve it over time, that the design
limits the cognitive burden because now
you can have a sense of knowing, well,
where am I in the system? Where does
this code live within the system, right?
And if you find code that's touching too
many places in the system, that sounds
to me like a design smell or or what you
call red flag. Like to me That would be
a red flag. Yeah. Yeah, I have to touch
five modules in order to get this new
functionality.
Sometimes you have to do it, and that's
the best you can do, but it's definitely
a red flag. That's the kind of thing
where if I saw that, I would say,
"Suppose Suppose I made the rule we
simply can't do this. I simply will not
do this. What would happen? Would I have
to simply shut the system down? Or could
I find some other way that gets around
this problem?" And what's interesting is
once If you see a red flag, and you say,
"Suppose I must eliminate this red
flag," you almost always can. Mhm. Yeah,
and that's one of the things too where
you mentioned sometimes you have to
touch five modules. The problem is when
the sometimes becomes, "Well, this is
just how we do it now." Because nobody
stopped and did the design thinking to
say, "Why are we having to touch five
modules every time we need to make a
change like this?" Yeah, I'm not really
good with the the argument, "Well, this
is how we do it." So, I realize that
that may be a a necessity in some
environments, but Well, and I didn't
even mean it necessarily as an argument.
And I didn't even necessarily mean it as
an argument, just more as a reality.
Meaning I think people people become
There's a sense where people's pain
tolerance increases with familiarity.
And so, if you're touching the same five
modules over and over again to make a
certain kind of change without a design
review or design thinking, I think
people can just think that even if they
don't state it, it's just how we do it.
It just becomes how they do it. As
opposed to saying, "Could we simplify
the design by putting all that
complexity together in a module so that
we're not having to touch five modules
every time?" Yeah, I'm I'm more of a rip
the band-aid off kind of person where I
I want to constantly expose these things
and get people thinking about them. But
again, I recognize, well, if you're
building a commercial product, there are
certain constraints you have to work
under. Sure. It's dangerous to let
yourself to let those become too
ingrained in you to the point where you
you no longer realize the cost that
they're incurring. Yeah, that's right.
And that's where I think again those
having those red flags at the ready to
be able to say, "Are we
Are we having Are we experiencing a red
flag here? What can we do about it?" And
then comparing that to the pros and
cons, cuz there's always trade-offs. And
maybe you're not going to fix it today,
but you know you're going to have to fix
it soon. And then you start thinking,
"Well, well, how can we do that
incrementally and improve bit by bit
instead of just accumulating the same
mess over and over again?" So, let's
talk now a little bit about We've talked
about interfaces to modules and modules
themselves and what they do, but someday
we actually have to implement something.
So, one of the design principles is that
working code isn't enough. Now, this
sounds like a challenge to me, and I
know you like putting challenges out
there and making theories. So, when I
hear working code, I think of certain
books like, you know, maybe clean code
or certain aspects of the you know, the
agile methodologies that say, "What we
care about is working code." But you say
it's not enough. So, speak to that a
little bit and how maybe that disagrees
with what the broader prevailing wisdom
might say. Well, who can object to code
that works, first of all? So, you might
you might say, "How can I
How can I not be satisfied?" That That's
unreasonable. Okay, so you're swimming
upstream here, so No,
what I would say is actually, yes. Yes,
working code is the ultimate goal, but
it's not just working code today.
It's working code tomorrow and next year
and the year after that. What project
can you point to and say, "This project
has already invested more than half of
the total effort that will ever be
invested in this project?"
It'd be hard to point to anyone. Most of
your investment in software is in the
future for any project. And so, the most
important thing I would argue is to make
that
future development go fast. As opposed
to You don't want to make trade-offs for
today that make your future development
go more slowly. And so, that's the key
idea. That and that's what I call I call
the the working code approach the
tactical approach where we just focus on
fixing the next bug or the next
deadline.
And if you add a few extra bits of
complexity in order to that, you argue,
"Well, that's okay cuz we got finished
faster." And I contrast that to the
strategic approach where the goal is to
produce the best design so that in the
future we can also develop as fast as
possible. Of course, other people use
the word technical debt, which is a
great way of characterizing this. You're
basically borrowing from the future when
you code tactically.
You're saving a little time today, but
you're going to pay it back with
interest in the future. And so, that's
why I argue for you should be thinking a
little bit ahead. You need to be
thinking about what will allow us to
develop fast, not just today, but next
year also. Yeah, I just had a episode a
few months ago with Ipek Ozkaya, and she
co-wrote a book. She's from the the
IEEE, and we'll put a link in the show
notes. Her book is called Managing
Technical Debt. And you mentioned before
the idea of investing in design. And
it's similar concept now too is view
this as an investment, and there's debt,
and the debt will have interest, and you
will need to pay that interest at some
point. And so, that concept relates very
much to the concepts in that book. So,
speaking of of technical debt and the
and the ways we tackle those things, you
mentioned a second ago the difference
between being strategic and being
tactical. And I'd like to explore that a
little bit more because in the book you
coined one of my favorite phrases now,
which is is hard to avoid using too
often, which is the idea of a tactical
tornado. So, maybe explain for our
listeners what a tactical tornado is,
and then how good design can help
prevent the tactical tornado syndrome.
Every organization has at least one
tactical tornado. I've worked with them.
I bet you've worked with them. When I
ask for a show of hands when I give
talks about how many of you have worked
with technical tornadoes, virtually
everybody raises their hands. Actually,
then I ask, "How many of you think you
might be a technical tornado?" And it's
surprising how many people will raise
their hand. A tactical tornado is is the
ultimate tactical programmer. Do
whatever it takes to make progress
today, no matter how much damage it
causes in the system. Often, you see
this is This is a person that will get a
project 80% of the way working and then
abandon it to go on to the next project.
They do the the first chunk, make
tremendous progress,
and leave it to other people to clean up
all the mess at the end. Or the person
that will, you know, when there's a bug
that needs to get fixed overnight, oh,
they'll fix it.
But they'll introduce two more bugs that
other people have to come along later
on. And what's ironic about them is
often managers consider these people
heroes.
Oh, yeah, if I need something done in a
hurry, I can just go to so-and-so,
they'll get it done. And then everybody
else has to come along and clean up
after them. And sometimes
to those people, so-and-so are like,
"I'm not getting any work done because
I'm cleaning up so-and-so's problems."
And so, every organization has them. I
just I think what you need is management
that doesn't support those people.
Recognizes again that these people are
doing damage and not just not just
fixing the bug, but also think about all
the other damage they do.
And I assume you've worked with tactical
tornadoes over your career. Well, I
think there's another category, which is
recovering tactical tornadoes that you
you didn't mention. Do you need an
intervention with them? Well, meaning if
you go back far enough in my career,
there was a time where that moniker
probably would have applied to me. But
that's going way back. But I think
that's another category is, you know,
there's there's individuals who are
Yeah, most people are trying to do the
right thing, but maybe the incentives
are are not set up properly. Or the
system, you know, the general system
around them is maybe not oriented to
help them, you know, fall into the pit
of success, right? Or or or the tendency
to do the right thing. So, I imagine for
a lot of people who are doing that, it's
not necessarily that they're nefarious
or they just want to pass off all their
all their work to somebody. There may be
some, but I think for a lot of people,
it's just a recognition of We've
mentioned technical empathy before and
things like this is, "Am I leaving bad
things in my wake for the people behind
me?" And so, I think you mentioned one
is management support, but then I think
also just a cultural ethos of we try to
build things that make other people's
lives easier and not just do things that
make me look good or or make it easy for
me.
Yes, I think education
is a big part of that. You need to
recognize when it happens and talk to
the people and explain the problems with
their approach. And hopefully you can
convert them.
I had a humorous experience in a recent
startup I was involved in where
a new engineer came on board. We had a a
very strong culture of unit testing at
the company. And so, all our software
had
pretty much 100% code coverage unit
tests.
This engineer came in, apparently wasn't
used to having unit tests. And he came
in and said, "Wow, this is fantastic. I
can make changes so quickly, and I just
run the unit tests and everything works.
These unit tests are fantastic." And
then after a week or two, and the person
had pushed a bunch of commits, I went
back and said, "Um
you haven't added any unit tests for the
code you wrote." And he said, "Oh, I
need to write unit tests?" And somehow
was not able to make the tie-in between
the benefit he received from unit tests
and the importance of actually writing
them. So, we had a talk, and he started
doing unit tests, and everything was
fine after that. But it had just never
occurred to him that he should also have
to write unit tests. Oh, that's
hilarious. Well, then my other favorite
is when people talk about refactoring
and they don't have test coverage. And I
say, "Well, refactoring is changing the
implementation without changing the
external behavior." And and the even
worse one is when they're changing the
unit tests constantly
when they change the implementation.
It's going
Just think about that for a minute. If
if somebody, you know, who was testing
your automobile did that, would you
really trust that car? You'd probably be
terrified.
Yeah, it's funny how those things sneak
in. But that that's a great point, too,
right? That that often people are
teachable. Maybe they just don't know
they don't know better. And then having
that team culture that says this is how
we do things and then helping introduce
people to it can definitely help.
Another design principle regarding
implementation, and I think some
explanation here will be helpful. The
increments of software development
should be abstractions, not features.
Now, we talked a second ago about how
certain managers might really like those
tactical tornadoes, and I imagine they
might hear this and say, "Hold on a
minute. You're telling me the
increments, which I imagine you mean the
deliveries of software development,
should be abstractions, not features."
And they're going TO CRY OUT, "WHERE ARE
MY FEATURES?" WELL, OKAY, so like all
design principles, this one doesn't
apply everywhere. And of course, there
are places where features matter.
I list this principle mostly in reaction
to test-driven design, where in which
you don't really do any design. You
write a set of tests for the
functionality you want.
And then which all of which break
initially. And then the software
development process consists of simply
going through making those tests pass
one after another until you eventually
have all the features you want.
And the problem with this is that
there's never really a good point to do
design. And so you tend to just kind of
throw things together. This tends to
produce really bad designs. And so what
I would argue is as much as possible
when you're adding on to your system,
try and do that by creating new
abstractions.
When you go and do it, build the whole
abstraction. Don't just build the one
tiny piece of the abstraction that you
need right now. Think about Think about
what the the real abstraction would be.
Now, that said, of course, there's the
top level in your system where you're
building features. Yeah, yeah. So that
that system is going to be all about
that part of the system will be all
about adding features. But most of your
system, hopefully, is these underlying
modules that get used. Sure. Although I
I guess it depends on how you define
feature, but from my standpoint, it's
it's sort of like there is no spoon in
the matrix. There is no features.
Features are emergent properties of a
composition of well-designed components.
And that's just how the world works. So
nobody nobody's actually building
features. But good you know, good luck
explaining this to
managers. Eyes glaze over and they say,
"But I want my features." It's Well,
you'll get your features, but I I guess
I you know, for me, I'd I'd push this
this principle a little bit further and
and say it's it's maybe closer to
axiomatic from my perspective that it
absolutely should be abstractions and
and not features. But again, that that's
also dependent on how you define
feature, of course. Yeah, again, this is
a way of thinking about, I think, when
you're doing agile design. Again, as you
What are the units you're adding on to
your system? And then that's why I would
say it should mostly be abstractions.
Yeah, so you talked about test-driven
design and and there's TDD, which could
mean test-driven development or
test-driven design. So maybe talk about
that a little bit more cuz that sounds
like that could be controversial for
some some listeners. You're
I should Sorry, I misspoke. I meant
test-driven development.
Oh, okay. So you didn't mean the same
thing. And so the implication there is
that we have these tests and then we
build our software, but that that can
lead to a bad design is what you're
stating.
Yes. I I think it's highly likely to
lead to a bad design.
So I'm not a fan of TDD. I think it's
better to again, build a whole
abstraction, and then I think actually
better to write the tests afterwards.
See, when I write tests, I tend to do
white box testing. That is,
I look at the code I'm testing and I
write tests to test that code. That way
I can make sure, for example, that that
every loop has been tested and every
condition, every if statement has been
tested, and so on. So how do you avoid
coupling your tests to the
implementation in that kind of an
environment? Well, there's some risk of
that. But then I mostly argue, is that a
problem or is that a feature? And so the
the risk of that is that when you make
change the implementation, you may have
to make significant changes to your
tests. And so that's not that's not a
bad thing except that it's extra work. I
don't see any The only problem with that
is it just takes longer to to do it. So
as long as you're not doing that a lot,
as long as you're not having to massive
refactoring your tests all the time,
then then I'd I'm okay with that.
But you know, this is an area which I
may just other people might disagree
with me on this one. Yeah, and and this
isn't the show where I I push your ideas
against mine, but that might be a fun
conversation to have in maybe another
another context. But you did mention
though that you you encourage starting
with the abstraction and then writing
your tests against that. And so that
that does sound like that could lend
also towards more, you know, opaque
testing as opposed to, you know,
testing the the implementation directly.
Yeah. Again, I when I write tests, I
don't actually test the abstraction. I
tend to test the implementation. That's
actually the way I tend to do it.
And just because I feel like I can I can
test more thoroughly. If I don't look at
the implementation at all, I think it's
more likely that there going to be
things that I'm not going to notice to
test. By the way, I will say there's a
the failure of my approach to testing
First, it's very good at catching errors
of commission,
where you do something you shouldn't do.
It's not so good at testing errors of
omission.
That is, if you fail to implement
something, then you're not going to test
for it, and you won't notice that. And
so if there's something you should be
doing that your code doesn't do at all,
this style of testing will not get that.
Maybe if you tested from the
abstraction, maybe you would think about
that, and maybe you'd write a test that
would catch that.
Well, and this where I'll join your camp
on TDD in the sense of I think that's
one of the that's one of the struggles
of TDD is I don't think it works once a
system gets beyond a certain amount of
simplicity because you just cannot
conceive of enough tests to actually
have the full functionality emerge. It's
impossible. There's there's diminishing
returns on the amount of time you can
spend defining those tests, and you will
never have enough tests to have a full
complex system emerge from that. And and
as you pointed out, it can also lead to
poor design. So listeners can definitely
have fun interacting with you on your
Google Groups channel after the show
about about TDD. Let's keep it keep it
civil, people. There is actually one
place where I agree that TDD is a good
idea. And that's when fixing bugs.
Before you fix a bug, you should add a
unit test that triggers the bug.
Make sure the unit test fails.
Then fix the bug and make sure the unit
test passes because otherwise you run
the risk that you haven't actually fixed
the bug. 100%. I'd also say, and I think
you'll agree, that's another element of
a good design is that you can do what
you just described. And if you can't do
what you just described, you should be
asking yourself how to improve the
design so that you can. Yeah, that says
something is not testable somehow. Yeah.
Exactly. So testability is another
hallmark. And and specifically what you
just said because I agree. If you can
write a failing test that exposes the
error condition first, then you have
confidence when that test passes that
you solved that problem. And of course,
if your other tests still pass, you know
you haven't accidentally broken
something else, at least that was tested
previously. You still You still could
have broken something else, but it
wasn't something that you were testing
previously. So it it does increase your
confidence, which is which is good.
Comments should describe things that are
not obvious from the code. I have a
feeling this principle might also be
slightly controversial. This principle
is controversial in that there seems to
be a fairly large group of people who
think that
comments are not needed,
or even
comments are a bad idea.
For example, Robert Martin in his book
Clean Code, which is I think one of the
most popular
books on software design. It's certainly
way farther up the Amazon list of most
of best-selling books than my book is,
for example. He says, and I believe the
direct quote is,
"Every comment is a failure." Wow.
And the implication is that if you had
to write a comment,
it means you failed to make everything
clear from your code. Well, I disagree
with this point. I think that
fundamentally,
it is not possible to describe in code
all the things that people need to know
in order to understand that code. You
simply cannot do that.
And that's the purpose of comments. So
for example,
in an interface, there are certain
things you cannot describe in comments.
If one method must be called before
another one,
there's no way in in any modern
programming language where you can
describe that
in the code itself.
And there's just many other examples. If
you look at any piece of code, there are
things that are important that people
need to know
that simply can't be described in the
code.
And so if you want to have abstraction,
if you really want to hide complexity,
you have to have comments to do that.
The alternative is you have to read the
code of the module
in order to understand it. That's not If
you have to read the code, then you're
exposed to all of that internal
complexity. You haven't hidden any
complexity.
So I I'm a very strong advocate of
comments. Now, I recognize that people
sometimes don't write good comments. And
you know, the flip side of this is that
the other mistake you can make is
writing a comment that simply duplicates
what's in the code. We've all seen the
comment add one to variable I followed
by the statement I equals I plus one.
Yes. Those comments are useless. Yes.
Because they're simply repeating what's
in the code.
Or another example, I bet you've seen
this. Every developer seen. You go and
you read the documentation.
And you read the for example, the the
JavaDocs for a method or the Doxygen
documentation.
And there will be a method called handle
page fault.
And what will the comment at the top
say?
Handle a page fault. Yeah.
So what has that comment added that
wasn't already obvious from the code?
The word a. There's no useful
information there.
So this is a dual double-edged sword.
It's really important to think about
what is not obvious from the code,
and document that. At the same time,
don't waste your time writing comments
that simply repeat
what you can get from the code. So when
you're documenting a method, use
different words from the variable name.
Don't use the same words. Or worse, the
comments don't match what the
implementation actually does, which I
think is part of the reason that Robert
Martin might speak against that. But the
ability to make bad comments is not a
reason to have no comments, I think is
something you would agree with.
a risk there's a risk that comments can
to stale. That's one of the four excuses
people use for not writing comments.
They say they're going to become stale
anyway, so why bother?
But in my experience,
it's not that difficult to keep comments
mostly up to date. There will
occasionally be errors, but almost all
the comments will still be accurate.
Yeah, and if people are using the
software and are using the documentation
to help them know how to use the
software, then that can also be a way to
keep them up to date if they're not
reflecting reality any longer. Right,
and the other thing is to think about
where you put your comments, which is
you want the comments as close as
possible to the code
that they're describing, so that if you
change the code, you're likely to see
the comment and change it also. Right,
which I would argue is true for all
documentation, meaning the closer your
documentation lives to the abstractions
and implementations, the better and the
more likely it will be kept up to date.
So, one last principle that I want to
talk about before we wrap up, software
should be designed for ease of reading,
not ease of writing. I think this
definitely relates to some things we
said previously, but talk a little bit
more about what does that mean, ease of
reading versus ease of writing and how
does that play out in software systems
in your experience? Well, there are
various shortcuts you could often use
that make code a little bit easier to
write, but make it harder to read. Two
classic examples, pet peeves of mine
about C++.
The first one is the keyword auto, which
you can use to say, "I'm not going to
tell you what type of variable this is.
You, madam compiler, please figure it
out on your own and just use the right
type."
It's super convenient and easy to use,
but now when somebody reads the code,
they have no way of They have to go
through themselves basically and repeat
the compiler's method to try to figure
out what type of thing this is. Another
one is standard pair,
this pair abstraction with a first and a
second.
Super easy if you need to return two
values from a method, just return a
pair.
But the problem now is that everybody's
referring to the elements of this result
as result.first and result.second, and
who knows what those actually are in
fact?
So,
the code was a little bit easier to
write. You didn't have to spend the time
to define a custom structure to return
these things, but it's much harder to
read.
Not putting comments in is another
example. It's It makes it faster to
write the code, but harder to read. And
there's there's a variety of other
things. So, I just if you just keep that
in mind and and ask yourself, is am I
making this code as easy as possible to
read, even if it takes you more time as
a writer, the thing is that code will be
read a lot more times than it was
written, and so it pays for itself. The
code will be read a lot more often than
it's written, and also the maintenance
life cycle of the code will vastly
exceed the development life cycle of the
code. You know, one of the problems I
think people forget People forget that
they forget. When they're writing the
code, they they don't think about the
fact that even if I come back to this in
3 months, I'm not going to remember why
I did this.
Yeah, that's right. That's why it's so
important sometimes to do a git blame on
code and then recognize that you were
the one who did it, right? That's just
It's a very important experience for
everyone. Who wrote this terrible code?
Git blame. Okay, I'm going to be quiet
now. Yeah, that's right. That's right.
Very important experience. John,
anything else that you want to cover
that maybe we've missed or or any
closing thoughts? No, I think you've
covered just about everything. This has
been a really fun conversation. I agree,
and I definitely encourage listeners to
get your book. And my understanding too
is there's a Google group that they can
join if they want to continue the
conversation with you from here. That is
correct. I think it's called software
designbook@googlegroups.com.
Great, and we'll definitely put a link
to that in the show notes as well. If
listeners want to find you on Twitter,
is it JohnOusterhout, @JohnOusterhout?
Uh yes, I believe that's right. They can
always just Google me too, and that'll
probably get them started on finding.
But I'm But I'm on Twitter, yep. And I'm
happy to take email. As I said at the
beginning, I don't claim to have all the
answers. I'm still learning myself. The
act of teaching the course has actually
changed my opinions about software
design in a few ways, and so I'm eager
to continue learning. So, if there are
things you see in the book that you
think are wrong-headed, I'd love to hear
why you think that. Or if you have other
design ideas that you think are really
important that I haven't mentioned, I'd
love to hear those as well.
And if you think there's a parallel
universe, getting back to our very
leading off question about whether
design is absolute or relative, if you
think there's an alternative universe of
design that is totally disjoint from
what I talk about and yet a really good
world, I'd love to hear about that as
well. Awesome. Awesome. I I love that
perspective. I I love your temperament
and your desire to just learn, and I
think the ability to be a lifelong
learner is a critical skill I think in
our industry. So, thanks for just
demonstrating that for us in in the way
you approach these things. Well, thanks
for the conversation. I've enjoyed it.
All right. Well, everyone, thanks so
much for joining John and I today on
Software Engineering Radio, and this is
Jeff Doolittle. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine.
For more about the podcast, including
other episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
se-radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.